Okay, בוקר טוב Boker Tov everybody and שבוע טוב, Shavua Tov, גוט
יום טוב. Gut Yom Tov. We now have the ימים טובים Yamim
Tovim behind us, so hopefully not so many disruptions in terms of
the schedule. And we now start the last פרק Perek of Sanhedrin,
פרק חלק. Perek Chelek. So let me start, we started yesterday, but
let me start by saying one or two introductory comments. The first
one is actually a correction of something that I said the other
day when we were before יום טוב, Yom Tov, which was the
order of the פרקים Prokim when we started אלו הן הנחנקים. Elu
Hen Hanhenakim. You know, and I mentioned at that time that some
have חלק Chelek as the tenth פרק Perek and אלו הן הנחנקים
Elu Hen Hanhenakim as the eleventh, but that you know, logically it
made sense to see this as the last because after you go
through all the מיתות בית דין, Misas Beis Din, there's a discussion
about like, you know, עולם הבא, Olam Ha-ba, like the assumption that
מיתות בית דין Misas Beis Din is מכפר, Mechaper, so even if
somebody did one of these terrible sins, they get executed by the
court, they get atoned for, but there's a small number of people
that don't have a חלק לעולם הבא. Chelek L'olam Ha-ba. And then
that's sort of like the end focus and then it sort of
ends with, you know, more of a whole agadic section.
But then I noted that the, and that's what Rashi says and
that's why we have the order we do. But I noted that,
you know, the ירושלמי Yerushalmi has the order reversed. And over יום
טוב Yom Tov I was continuing to look at it, the תוספתא
Tosefta also has the order reversed. It's very clear in the תוספתא
Tosefta because it's more embedded that this comes before and that אלו
הן הנחנקים Elu Hen Hanhenakim comes afterwards. And then I relooked at
it and I realized that it was actually, that is that the
correct order is actually the reverse of what we have. Because the
last משנה, Mishna, there's one of the ארבע מיתות Arba Misos of
הרג Hereg that we haven't done. אלו הנשרפין, Elu Hanisrafin, שרפה Srefa
and הרג, Hereg, and there's one that we haven't done, which was
עיר הנדחת. Ir Nidachas. And עיר הנדחת Ir Nidachas gets mentioned at
the end of חלק. Chelek. So actually the order actually has to
be the second to last because, you know, you did שרפה, Srefa,
you did חנק, Chenek, you know, for whatever reason we have this
digression in the middle, but then it ends with the last one
of
חנק—excuse Chenek me, הרג—you Hereg did שרפה Srefa and הרג, Hereg, by
הרג Hereg you had רציחה, Retzicha, and there are two people that
get הרג, Hereg, death by the sword: the רוצח Rotzeach and the
עיר הנדחת. Ir Nidachas. Okay, so then the end of חלק Chelek
is the עיר הנדחת Ir Nidachas and that's the end of הרג,
Hereg, and then חנק Chenek is the חנק. Chenek. So clearly חלק
Chelek does become—and that's clearly the order of the ירושלמי Yerushalmi and
of the תוספתא, Tosefta, which then just raises the question, which is
why have a major section in the middle about who gets a
חלק לעולם הבא Chelek L'olam Ha-ba right before you get to even
finishing discussing, you know, who the ארבע מיתות בית דין Arba Misos
Beis Din are and so on. Now I don't have a full
answer. Part of the answer is that when it gets to עיר
הנדחת Ir Nidachas it says, it discusses whether אנשי עיר הנדחת Anshei
Ir Nidachas have a חלק לעולם הבא Chelek L'olam Ha-ba or not.
So you could sort of see this as a way that we're
going to lead up to this whole city that gets wiped out.
Right, that's a pretty horrific thing and you know they've mentioned there's
even a discussion about what do you do with the innocents that
are there and so on. So like you know, because it's such
a radical punishment, you know, you want to sort of discuss in
that context more than you do in the other context. Other מיתות
בית דין, Misas Beis Din, they have a חלק לעולם הבא, Chelek
L'olam Ha-ba, so anyway, so to some degree you could understand that
like we're sort of building up to that. It's still a lot
of build-up to discuss the issue of עיר הנדחת Ir Nidachas has
a חלק לעולם הבא. Chelek L'olam Ha-ba. The other thing to mention
is that in the context of discussing רוצח, Rotzeach, we managed to
discuss some general principles about מיתות Misas like that weren't limited to
the specific מיתות בית דין. Misas Beis Din. Right? Within רוצח Rotzeach
we got to other ways in which people were executed. Right? We
got the case
about the רודף, Rodef, we had the case of the, before רודף,
Rodef, who else did we have? Of the בא במחתרת, Ba B'machteres,
right? You know, the which is a type of a רודף. Rodef.
And then you had the whole sort of example of the רודף
Rodef and then you had the people that you would execute because
they committed murder even if they could not be proven, you know,
to have actually have done it, or the people that got multiple
lashes of בית דין. Beis Din. Then you got the case of
קנאים פוגעין בו. Kanaim Pogin Bo. So you started to discuss things
which weren't about formal מיתות בית דין Misas Beis Din but more
general ways in which people and their sins and they're punished for
or society responds to and so on. So to some degree, I
mean it's still a bit of a jump, that's still very this-worldly
and then you're jumping to like other-worldly, although there was also a
mention about who gets מיתה בידי שמים. Misa Bi-yedei Shamayim. So for
some reason, and I again I can't really understand this fully, but
there was a decision that like okay since we're having these broader
discussions that are not limited to מיתות בית דין Misas Beis Din
about types of punishments or whatever, you know, this-worldly and other-worldly punishments,
let's discuss who gets עולם הבא. Olam Ha-ba. Okay, but eventually anyway,
so that's in terms of just you know whether this is intended
as the end of the מסכת. Masechet. It's clear as you'll see
the end of the פרק Perek is about עיר הנדחת Ir Nidachas
and it really seems that it really is the second to last
פרק Perek and not the last פרק. Perek. So we're going to
assume the actual order of חלק Chelek is correct, meaning because you
could have thought that, well, within חלק Chelek is correct, yeah, yeah,
and of course then the way it ends is it ends with
עיר הנדחת Ir Nidachas and... Now that we're done with people who
get הרג, Hereg, now let's move on to חנק, Chenek, and then
the next פרק Perek could have been אלו הן הנחנקים. Elu Hen
HaNechnakim. Okay, so that's, I don't know, for the Talmudists, Talmudists among
us that's... I mean the academic Talmudists that was maybe interesting, maybe
less so for some people, but more at least anyway interesting for
me in terms of the order of the פרקים. Perakim. But...
Oh, I'm sorry, thank you, yes, oh, I forgotten, yes, today is
also the, I'm sorry I meant to mention that today is the
יארצייט Yahrtzeit of Henry Gutman, חנוך בן חיים יוסף, Chanoch ben Chaim
Yosef, and our learning should be in his memory, his memory should
have an עליה, Aliyah, his נשמה Neshama should have an עליה. Aliyah.
So now so let's talk about what I think more people are
interested in, which is the major theme of this פרק, Perek, which
is עולם הבא, Olam HaBa, and who gets a portion in עולם
הבא. Olam HaBa. And here it's important to
mention a very important question and issue right at the outset, which
is what does the גמרא Gemara mean when it refers to עולם
הבא? Olam HaBa? Normally we assume that עולם הבא Olam HaBa means
the world of souls where your soul goes to after you die,
right, so that it's not that it's a future world that's in
a later time as meaning subjectively, it's the next world for me,
right, where my soul will be after I die, but it's not
some future world that doesn't exist now, it exists some parallel world
of the souls. Okay, that is רמב"ם Rambam's idea of עולם הבא,
Olam HaBa, that is not at all the פשט Peshat of this
גמרא, Gemara, of this entire פרק. Perek. And you see that from
the fact that the פרק Perek begins with who doesn't have a
חלק, Chelek, a portion in the world to come, somebody who is
כופר בתחיית המתים, Kofer be-Techiyat HaMeitim, who denies resurrection of the dead.
And the גמרא Gemara says why does that person not have a
portion in the world to come? And it says well, if you
deny resurrection of the dead, if you deny it, you're not going
to get it. So as the ריטב"א Ritva says, who was talking
about resurrection of the dead? We were talking about עולם הבא. Olam
HaBa. So so what? You don't get תחיית המתים, Techiyat HaMeitim, what
does that have to do with עולם הבא? Olam HaBa? So from
the גמרא Gemara it's very clear that the גמרא Gemara understands that
תחיית המתים Techiyat HaMeitim is a period that leads into עולם הבא.
Olam HaBa. And that פשט, Peshat, and it's obviously clear if you
read the גמרא Gemara and you read the משניות Mishnayot and whatever,
it's very explicit that עולם הבא Olam HaBa means the world that
will follow this world, not subjectively, objectively for all humanity,
okay, in time, that after there will be an end to sort
of this worldly history, there'll be a Messianic period, משיח Mashiach will
come,
the dead will rise, and then there'll be a different type of
a world that will be created. What we're actually going to see
that's coming up in the גמרא, Gemara, the גמרא Gemara believes actually
further that for a thousand years there will be no world at
all, God will just wipe the slate clean and then create a
new world, okay, and what's going to be in that new world?
Will that be a world where just the souls exist or will
that be a world because תחיית המתים Techiyat HaMeitim precedes it, many
ראשונים Rishonim believe that no, it'll be a world that will still
be in our bodies, but maybe it'll be fundamentally a spiritual world.
The גמרא Gemara says in עולם הבא Olam HaBa there is no
drinking and no eating but the צדיקים Tzaddikim sit with their crowns
on their heads and they and they derive benefit from the glow
of the presence of the שכינה. Shekhinah. So does that mean that
there are no physical bodies and we're just living in a disembodied
spiritual state? That's certainly a reasonable read of that, or right, right,
or you could say there'll be a miracle of תחיית המתים, Techiyat
HaMeitim, then they'll die and whatever and they'll have עולם הבא Olam
HaBa for the נשמות, Neshamot, but since תחיית המתים Techiyat HaMeitim is
understood as a necessary lead-in for עולם הבא, Olam HaBa, the many
ראשונים Rishonim that read the גמרא Gemara in its simple sense, which
starts with the רמב"ן, Ramban, it's ראב"ד, Ra'avad, the רמב"ן, Ramban, the
ריטב"א Ritva and so on, they basically read no, we'll be in
our bodies, but our bodies will be on such a high spiritual
level that our bodies won't need physical sustenance and we'll still be
basically a spiritual existence but an embodied spiritual existence. I don't know,
we'll worry about it when we get to the
גמרא. Gemara. So exactly, they give that example like משה Moshe on
הר סיני Har Sinai will be so close to God that we'll
be getting sustenance from the presence of God but we will be
still embodied. Okay, so now
רמב"ם Rambam is very against
this because רמב"ם Rambam just philosophically he doesn't like this whole idea
of why well, forget, I'm not going to get into a big
philosophical discussion right now, but I do want to say that there
are here are the different terms. I'll do this, identify different terms
in the גמרא Gemara and I'll tell you how most ראשונים Rishonim
read them according to the פשט Peshat of the גמרא Gemara and
then how רמב"ם Rambam reads them. Okay, so
he interprets it metaphorically. Okay, so anyway, so you
have גן עדן Gan Eden and גיהנום, Gehennom, okay, you have משיח,
Mashiach,
תחיית המתים, Techiyat HaMeitim,
עולם הבא, Olam HaBa, I think that's about it. I'm trying to
remember if there's something else. Oh, and then the other thing that
you have to deal with in terms of this economy as it
were is the whole rewards and punishments that are in the תורה,
Torah, right, like ונתתי גשמיכם בעתו. VeNatati Gishmeichem be-Ito.
okay? Because the question is what is the reward you're going to
get for
your doing your מצוות mitzvos and or punishment for עבירות? aveiros? Is
it this worldly, is it other worldly, how do you understand if
it's other worldly or whatever, okay? So what to do with the
fact that the תורה, Torah, number one, we should just notice, right,
that the תורה Torah itself is extremely this worldly. All right, so,
you know, all the rewards or whatever the ברכות berachos and the
קללות kelalos are all this worldly, right? The, I mean, then focusing
on that became a little difficult, you know, the more the problem
of צדיק ורע לו, tzadik v'ra lo, רשע וטוב לו rasha v'tov
lo was
heightened, you know, and so anyway so you know academics point out
whatever anyway so you know that there's a heightened discussions about future
rewards when things were you know when the Jews were subject to
persecutions and sufferings and martyrdom and it was very hard to explain
where is the this worldly reward. Okay, so what to do with
this and in general there was a shift away from this. רמב"ן
Ramban says that this is talking about like when all of כלל
ישראל Klal Yisrael is doing the מצוות, mitzvos, you know, the as
a, as a national level, it's not true at a personal level
in terms of being this worldly reward. Okay, רמב"ם Rambam says that
what the פסוקים pesukim mean is that they mean not that this
is your ultimate reward but that if you do מצוות mitzvos then
God will make life make it easier for you to continue to
do מצוות, mitzvos, meaning that the point is not to have a
good life in this world, but the only reason that God that
these ברכות berachos are given is a way of saying that if
you do bad then God will make things hard for you or
make it harder for you and and just continue to lead you
down a path of not doing מצוות mitzvos and if you do
good and do מצוות mitzvos God'll make things easier, you know, and
provide you, you know, the means to do more מצוות mitzvos or
whatever, anyway, either way nobody because of all of the emphasis on
the גמרא Gemara on otherworldly and because of the problems of צדיק
ורע לו, tzadik v'ra lo, right, the idea was was that that's
not really referring to how you ultimately get rewarded for your good
deeds. Okay, the simple explanation is like I said the רמב"ן, Ramban,
simple but anyway they're talking at a national level. So what do
you do with all of this? Okay. So what רמב"ם Rambam so
so a רמב"ן Ramban says is, right, as I said, this is
sort of like in, in future time, okay, future time, משיח Mashiach
will come, he'll be מחיה המתים, mechaye hamesim, we'll be עולם הבא,
olam haba, which'll be some type of future embodied spiritual existence but
it'll be embodied, okay? And that's, and obviously that would include the
idea that this will be a miraculous time, okay? What about this?
So the רמב"ם Rambam basically says that this is, well first of
all, okay, I should mention one of the things that's going to
happen in תחיית המתים techiyas hamesim is the גמרא Gemara says that
there's going to be like a יום הדין, Yom HaDin, okay? The
dead are going to arise and even the רשעים reshaim are going
to arise as we'll see in the later משניות, mishnayos, there'll be
some people that will be such רשעים reshaim that they won't even
be resurrected for the יום הדין Yom HaDin in the future time.
But most people, even the רשעים, reshaim, will be resurrected, not only
the צדיקים. tzadikim. Then they are all going to stand in a
future judgment in the future time. You said they weren't judged when
they died? They, well we'll get to that. Okay. They're all going
to stand in a future judgment at a future time, those that
are righteous will continue to live and will eventually stick around for
עולם הבא, olam haba, okay, and those that are wicked will get
basically sent to גיהנום Gehennom or other things will be done to
them, their bodies will be destroyed, their souls will be destroyed, whatever,
we'll worry about what happens. But anyway, but the righteous are the
ones that are going to make it to עולם הבא, olam haba,
but everybody's going to have a תחיית המתים. techiyas hamesim. Okay. So
then the question would be of course according to that which is
so what happens in the interim from the time you die until,
until this period? Okay. And interestingly enough there's many more sources, we
all assume when we focus on like the future reward and punishment
like what happens after you die, right, not this future time, but
there are much more in terms of the sources in the משניות
mishnayos and the גמרא Gemara about this. This really initially because if
you also you think about it in terms of the נביאים, nevi'im,
the prophets, right, their vision was about the future, right, what will
Israel be in the future, you know, whatever it was all very
future this-worldly but future oriented as opposed to what happens after you
die in some world of souls. But there are a few sources
about what's going about your like what's happened after you die, like
one the רמב"ן Ramban quotes is a famous one about what a
person you know saying קדיש Kaddish for the first twelve months or
not קדיש Kaddish but whatever you know after a parent dies, the
assumption about whether they're judged in גיהנום Gehennom for twelve months after
the death and so on, that there are גמרות, Gemaras, surprisingly based
on our way of thinking about it, much fewer, but there are
גמרות Gemaras that discuss a period of judgment whatever for the souls
after death. So the רמב"ם Rambam basically says that's like this, that's
like this period, okay, and that also exists like right now and
whatever גן עדן Gan Eden is two things, there's both the physical
גן עדן Gan Eden and a spiritual corresponding גן עדן Gan Eden
and this is where the souls go either to גן עדן Gan
Eden or גיהנום Gehennom while they're awaiting the future יום הדין. Yom
HaDin. But what is it based on? What? So but it's still
based on some
sort of
other גמרא. Gemara.
I mean well that's a good well that's a good question. Okay
we can talk right you're right. I mean like if you know
I mean the idea is still that there's a significance about you
mean like you understand why this would happen but why not just
have the right to be resurrected? What's the point of the wicked
being resurrected just to be judged again? Okay so we can talk
about that when we get to it. That's a good question. Okay
but anyway but this is basically this is normally the way this
is פשט pshat of the גמרא Gemara and our גמרא Gemara is
focus on this future time not on this. Okay רמב״ם Rambam does
not like any of this. Alright רמב״ם Rambam basically thinks that this
is all way too like since like who what's the point about
physical reward anyway? It's all about you know the developing of the
soul and the soul to I don't know whatever. He doesn't like
he doesn't like it. It's all too it's all too magical for
רמב״ם Rambam or miraculous. So basically רמב״ם Rambam first of all he
says משיח Moshiach is just does is not a is not a
special time. משיח Moshiach is just when there is a sovereignty in
Israel so now you understand why רב קוק Rav Kook thought it
was התחלתא דגאולה atchalta d'geula okay why it was sovereignty in Israel
and and people you know the physical situation is better the economic
situation is better so it's easier for people to do מצוות mitzvos
maybe it's a time where people eventually recognize you know like the
truth of the Jewish sort of faith whether it means the specific
particularist aspects of it or not is a question. But anyway משיח
Moshiach is just a future time when everybody's gonna when there'll be
sovereignty and people will be doing מצוות. mitzvos. Okay תחיית המתים techiyas
hameisim for רמב״ם Rambam is no big
I mean yes it's a tremendous miracle but he says okay so
there'll be some miracle in the future the dead will arise and
then they'll live their lives and then they'll die again okay? It's
not going to actually create a different type of a time. And
עולם הבא Olam Haba for רמב״ם Rambam is basically he completely pretty
much rules that out and for him the only meaningful עולם הבא
Olam Haba is where our souls go after we die. Okay and
even for him by the way there's another part about his whole
philosophy which is that he doesn't like it to be this idea
of reward and punishment where oh you were a good boy here's
your reward you'll get a high a big portion in עולם הבא
Olam Haba oh you were a bad boy you're going to suffer
in גיהינום. Gehennom. He sees exactly he sees it as very naturalistic.
That the more your soul apprehended God then the closer your soul
then the more you've actualized sort of the infinite potential and the
divine in your soul and therefore the more your soul is connected
to has an eternal life and is connected to the eternal after
it dies. And if the soul has sinned or whatever and been
distanced from God then it just doesn't continue to exist. So then
of course רמב״ן Ramban asks he says so then there's no different
degree of suffering? You could be a terrible רשע rasha or just
you know like the whole range of different degrees of wickedness right
like if the soul just doesn't exist like what's the whole you
know forget that he thinks that all the descriptions of גיהינום Gehennom
are all metaphors that's fine but I mean רמב״ן Ramban doesn't like
that either but okay. But the problem is like then where's the
justice in that? But for רמב״ם Rambam it's not really about justice
and reward it's about just the natural state of the soul. So
if the soul apprehended God it'll be with God in עולם הבא
Olam Haba and he doesn't like the גן עדן Gan Eden idea
either. He just says גן עדן Gan Eden is some place in
this world it's a nice place. He says maybe we'll find and
there'll be some good plants and we'll find some medicines we don't
know about. He actually says that. Anyway okay okay and גיהינום Gehennom
is just a metaphor and basically it's whether your soul continues to
whether if your soul lives on after death to the degree that
it's apprehended God or not. Okay very naturalistic. But aren't there these
גמרות Gemaras you know like בלעם Bilaam is in צואה רותחת? tzoah
rosochas? It's all a metaphor. Okay everything for רמב״ם Rambam is a
metaphor. Okay so that's basically what רמב״ם Rambam does with all of
that. It's right here. Yeah עולם הבא Olam Haba is the world
that exists per subjectively for us after we stop living. What about
the נביאים nevi'im though? What were the נביאים nevi'im doing then? What
do you mean? Oh there'll be a messianic period when things will
be good for the like you know for the good people. Right.
Anyway the רמב״ן Ramban רמב״ם Rambam did not like the way that
this I'll say one last thing and then we really should return
to the גמרא. Gemara. רמב״ם Rambam did not like the way that
the
you know people would waste their time speculating about what עולם הבא
Olam Haba is going to be like. The exact questions that the
גמרא Gemara asks which is like oh when the dead rise will
they be wearing their clothes or not wearing their clothes? Will they
be as old as they were when they died? If they had
a broken leg will they still have a broken leg? If a
guy's wife died and then he remarried a second wife who will
he be married to? Right? The רמב״ם Rambam says like this is
all idle silly speculation and we have to focus on this world
and you know and doing תורה Torah and doing מצוות mitzvos and
so on. And that was his emphasis was to get people to
like you know to downplay messianic times to focus on this world.
But David Berger wrote many decades ago what I thought was a
really insightful article where he said the result of רמב״ם Rambam
de-miraculizing I just made up that word anyway you know messianic times.
Because רמב״ם Rambam rules like שמואל. Shmuel. שמואל Shmuel says I think
I don't know if you saw this
the other day The only difference is whether we're going to have,
whether we're going to be subject to other nations or whether we're
going to have our own sovereignty. So שמואל Shmuel says that. רמב"ם
Rambam basically says that's the truth. It's a very subtle what רמב"ם
Rambam does. רמב"ם Rambam in משנה תורה Mishneh Torah says, אמרו חכמים
אין בין עולם הזה לימות המשיח. Amru chachamim ein bein olam hazeh
limot hamashiach.
He makes this one opinion of שמואל, Shmuel, which in the גמרא
Gemara is this very strange minority opinion, and he makes it as
if it's the collective voice of the rabbis. So one of the
נושאי כלים nosei kelim of the רמב"ם, Rambam, where רמב"ם Rambam says
אמרו חכמים אין בין עולם הזה, Amru chachamim ein bein olam hazeh,
one of the נושאי כלים nosei kelim says שמואל אמרה. Shmuel amrah.
So it's not
the חכמים. chachamim. But anyway, what David Berger said was that by
trying to de-miracularize that, to get us to not be so focused
on Messianic period, it had the reverse effect because it allowed people
that were claiming to be the Messiah or claiming a Messianic period
to say: Don't ask me to do miracles, just look at רמב"ם.
Rambam. רמב"ם Rambam says that it's not a miraculous time, as long
as you have a king that gathers the people, whatever. So he
identified three Messianic figures or
movements. שבתי צבי. Shabbetai Zvi. And שבתי צבי Shabbetai Zvi explicitly, he
or his נביא navi there, נתן Natan or whatever the guy's name
was, he's quoting the רמב"ם Rambam and says it doesn't have to
be a miracle and I could still be the Messiah and so
on. Number two, he said, was
religious Zionism, אתחלתא דגאולה, atchalta de'geulah, you can say it's Messianic periods
without it being obviously miraculous. And the Lubavitcher Rebbe. And he says
they quote the רמב"ם Rambam a lot. It doesn't have to be
miraculous. So the effect of saying that it's not going to be
a miraculous time actually wound up supporting claims for people who were
claiming to be the Messiah. Anyway, so that's a quick overview of
some of these issues. But yes, the simple גמרא Gemara is sort
of very much focused on this is the Messianic period. Yes, Charlie.
Yeah, in Christianity in the Middle Ages, they had every bit as
much speculation and a lot of evangelicals engage in this speculation today.
I'm sure they do. One quick question. People will still be giving
birth and
whatever? Presumably. That's a good question. According to רמב"ם, Rambam, not. I
mean, according to רמב"ם, Rambam, yes, excuse me. According to רמב"ם, Rambam,
there we're just going to, there'll be some miracle called תחיית המתים,
techiyat hameitim, we'll all be astounded and then get on with our
lives and world is going to be normal. And then people will
be born and die? Exactly. What about the other opinion though? That
we're still going to... Possibly not. That's true. Okay. So, if
you want to, the רמב"ן Ramban in שער הגמול Sha'ar HaGemul goes
through pretty much every single גמרא Gemara that deals with this and
tries to organize them and come up with the
whatever. And he basically lays this out and then he also spends
a lot of time just speaking about how mistaken
רמב"ם Rambam is. So anyway, where did we leave off?
אמרו רומיים. Amru Romayim. Where is that? Eleven lines down in the
big lines. One, two, three, four, five, six, seven, eight, nine, ten,
eleven. Yeah, mine too. שאלו רומיים Sha'alu Romayim את רבי יהושע בן
חנניה. et Rabbi Yehoshua ben Chananya. מנין שהקדוש ברוך
הוא מחיה מתים ויודע מה שעתיד להיות? Minayin she-Hakadosh Baruch Hu mechayeh
meitim ve-yodea mah she-atid lihyot? How do you know God will be
מחיה מתים? mechayeh meitim? Right,
because the point here is that it's not just תחיית המתים, techiyat
hameitim, but תחיית המתים מן התורה, techiyat hameitim min ha-Torah, and that
God knows the future. אמר להו תרווייהו מן המקרא הזה. Amar lehu
tarvaihu min ha-mikra hazeh. I can get it both from one פסוק.
pasuk. שנאמר, Shene'emar, ויאמר ה' אל משה הנך שכב עם אבותיך וקם.
Vayomer Hashem el Moshe hinecha shochev im avotecha ve-kam. You will lie
down with your fathers and you will rise up. That's the way
we read it before. So that's knowing both תחיית המתים, techiyat hameitim,
משה Moshe will arise, and also God knows the future. והעם הזה
וזנה. Ve-ha'am hazeh ve-zanah. So then they said to him, ודילמא וקם
העם הזה וזנה? Ve-dilma ve-kam ha'am hazeh ve-zanah? Maybe it doesn't mean
משה Moshe will rise up, maybe it means the people will arise
and they will fornicate. אמר להו נקוטו מיהא פלגא בידייכו. Amar lehu
nekutu miha palga bi-yadeichu. Okay, fine, so it didn't prove that תחיית
המתים, techiyat hameitim, but at least it proves God knows the future
even read your way, it says the people will rise up, so
God is predicting what'll happen in the future, יודע מה שעתיד להיות.
yodea mah she-atid lihyot. It seems funny, it seems like given all
the נביאים nevi'im are always prophesying
what'll be. Anyway, איתמר נמי Itmar nami אמר רבי יוחנן amar Rabbi
Yochanan משום רבי שמעון בן יוחאי. mishum Rabbi Shimon ben Yochai. מנין
שהקדוש ברוך הוא מחיה מתים ויודע מה שעתיד להיות שנאמר הנך שכב
עם אבותיך וקם. Minayin she-Hakadosh Baruch Hu mechayeh meitim ve-yodea mah she-atid
lihyot shene'emar hinecha shochev im avotecha ve-kam. Okay. תניא. Tanya. אמר רבי
אליעזר ברבי יוסי. Amar Rabbi Eliezer be-Rabbi Yosi. בדבר זה זייפתי ספרי
מינים. Bi-davar zeh ziyafti sifrei minim. With this thing I managed to
forge, I mean to show, the books of the מינים minim were
bogus. One minute, Charlie. Okay. Now the problem is that מינים minim
usually means Jewish Christians. Okay, but in this context it doesn't seem
to make sense because שהיו אומרים אין תחיית המתים מן התורה. she-hayu
omrim ein techiyat hameitim min ha-Torah. They would say that there's no
idea of resurrection from the תורה. Torah. I don't know historically, I
didn't check. I have a book that goes through all the גמרות
Gemarot that deals with... with Christianity, but like and tries to put
it in a historical context. But like you know, Christians of course
thought that Jesus rose and that they believed in the fact that
Jesus would come and there'll be a resurrection in the future times,
right? You know, so what does it mean? So what were they
saying, so it's not מן התורה? min HaTorah? Was I mean what
מינים minim were saying? It does not seem that this is the
classic מינים minim that are the Jewish Christians, right? It seems that
our משנה Mishnah should be mentioned as well, but our משנה Mishnah
that mentions the people that don't have a חלק לעולם הבא, chelek
l’olam haba, right, why did it mention only these? I mean that's
another discussion, right, which we'll get to later, which was like it's
not here giving a list of like here are our dogma, let's
right if we're going to list our dogma, let's start with like
you know God exists, תורה מן השמים, Torah min HaShamayim, whatever. Like
you know, it's not systematic, it doesn't it's not comprehensive. So you
know most scholars believe that the things that are highlighted in our
משנה Mishnah באין לו חלק לעולם הבא be’ein lo chelek l’olam haba
are because there were Jewish sectarians who actually rejected these beliefs. So
this was a specifically articulated as a way of saying those sectarians
are wrong and they're not going to have a חלק לעולם הבא.
chelek l’olam haba. So מינים minim could be a sectarian, you know
that's more specifically what it means than a Jewish Christian. Often it
means a Jewish Christian, but it seems here that we are very
specifically dealing with a type of Jewish sectarian that did not believe
in תחיית המתים techiyat hameitim or didn't believe that it was מן
התורה. min HaTorah. But in general, and this is the point to
make, that the משנה Mishnah when identifying these beliefs that are important
that you don't have a חלק לעולם הבא chelek l’olam haba
seems specifically to be in dialogue right with sectarians of the time.
Yes Charlie? Trani says that מינים minim is כותים. Kutim. Yeah, that
I- it's bizarre that he has that, clearly it's מינים... minim... really?
Well, oh really? I can't believe that. כותים? Kutim? Yeah. And he
has two expositions about it. He thinks that the- that would be
bizarre that the original text was כותים Kutim and then it was
changed to מינים. minim. That would be strange. Okay, he thinks that
this is referring to Samaritans' beliefs and the Samaritans didn't believe in-...
I got three paragraphs explanation of why that is. All right, I'll
take a look at it. I'm just- I was just skeptical not
because it couldn't be Samaritans' beliefs, but that because you normally have
the word מינים minim which is replaced with the word כותים. Kutim.
It's hard to understand why the original text would- I'd have to
check the manuscripts. Okay, that's very interesting. Okay, anyway, so okay maybe
it's Samaritans, some form-... צדוקים Tzadokim were the ones who didn't believe
in-... Right. Okay, some form of sectarians did not believe that תחיית
המתים techiyat hameitim was מן התורה min HaTorah and he says, I
show that their scripture was bogus. Okay. אמרתי להם, Amarti lahem, זייפתם
תורתכם ziyaftem toratchem ולא העליתם בידכם כלום. v'lo he'elitem beyadechem klum. You-
you have forged your own תורה. Torah. Now that would explain, by
the way, this is why I was thinking that maybe it was
about Christians, but it would-... the Samaritan reading would be good because
the Samaritans did have a different תורה, Torah, right? So the idea
of whose תורה Torah is authentic and who is forged works very
good in the Samaritan context. Okay, so you have forged your תורה,
Torah, you have corrupted your תורה. Torah. ולא העליתם בידכם כלום v'lo
he'elitem beyadechem klum שאתם אומרים אין תחיית המתים מן התורה, she'atem omrim
ein techiyat hameitim min HaTorah, הרי הוא אומר, harei hu omer, הכרת
תכרת הנפש ההיא עונה בה, hikaret tikaret hanefesh hahi avonah bah, הכרת
hikaret בעולם הזה, ba’olam hazeh, תכרת tikaret לעולם הבא. l’olam haba. עונה
בה למה? avonah bah l’eimat? When will its sin remain if it's
not just being cut off in this worldly punishment? לאו לעולם הבא?
lav l'olam haba? It means for the future. אמר ליה רב פפא
לאביי, Amar lei Rav Papa l’Abaye, ולימא להו תרוייהו v’leima lehu travaihu
מהכרת תכרת? mi-hikaret tikaret? So that means the fact that there's no
עולם הבא olam haba notice means there's no תחיית המתים. techiyat hameitim.
Right? If it's pun- meaning if it's punished with no עולם הבא,
olam haba, it means it won't get תחיית המתים. techiyat hameitim. But
it implicitly shows you that there is תחיית המתים techiyat hameitim because
it has to- because the discussion of עולם הבא olam haba implies
תחיית המתים, techiyat hameitim, right? Which is again this assumption that the
תחיית המתים techiyat hameitim leads to עולם הבא. olam haba. So since
it's cut off from עולם הבא, olam haba, it shows you that
there is a period of
תחיית המתים. techiyat hameitim. Okay. אמר ליה רב פפא לאביי, Amar lei
Rav Papa l’Abaye, ולימא להו תרוייהו v’leima lehu travaihu מהכרת תכרת? mi-hikaret
tikaret? אינהו הוו אמרי ליה inhu hava amri lei דברה תורה כלשון
בני אדם. dibrah torah k’lashon bnei adam. They wouldn't have been impressed
by the double language. So but the fact that there's הכרת תכרת
hikaret tikaret and עונה בה avonah bah shows that there's another period.
Okay. תניא, Tanaya, הכרת תכרת. hikaret tikaret. הכרת hikaret בעולם הזה, ba’olam
hazeh, תכרת tikaret לעולם הבא, l’olam haba, דברי רבי עקיבא. divrei Rabbi
Akiva. אמר ליה רבי ישמעאל, Amar lei Rabbi Yishmael, והלא כבר נאמר
v’lo kvar neemar את ה׳ הוא מגדף ונכרתה, et Hashem hu megadef
v’nichretah, which he understands is also talking about
עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, הכרת תכרת. hikaret tikaret. No, it's a different
פסוק, pasuk, that's a פסוק pasuk about
מגדף. megadef. And this is a-... Is it the
same פסוק? pasuk? I don't know. Okay, so he says they're all
about
עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. וכי שלוש עולמים יש? v’chi shalosh olamim yesh?
There's only two, עולם הזה olam hazeh and עולם הבא. olam haba.
אלא ונכרתה בעולם הזה הכרת לעולם הבא. ella v'nichretah ba'olam hazeh hikaret
l'olam haba. הכרת תכרת, hikaret tikaret, דברה תורה כלשון בני אדם. dibrah
torah k’lashon bnei adam. So you see Rabbi Yishmael says the double
language doesn't mean anything. But everybody agrees it's עולם הזה olam hazeh
and עולם הבא. olam haba. Okay, בין רבי ישמעאל בין רבי עקיבא,
bein Rabbi Yishmael bein Rabbi Akiva, עונה בה מאי עבדי ביה? avonah
bah mai avdi beh? But since they both- one learns it out
from the הכרת תכרת hikaret tikaret and one learns it out from
two separate פסוקים psukim about כרת, karet, so neither learns out עולם
הבא olam haba from עונה בה. avonah bah. So what do they
learn out from
עונה בה? avonah bah? לכדתניא. L’chidetnaya. Fine. So that's the Rome—the question
of the Romans and the question of
the
מינים Minim or the כותים. Kutim. שאלה קליאופטרה מלכתא את רבי מאיר.
Sha'alah Cleopatra Malketa Et Rabbi Meir. Okay, do the dates work? I
don't think so. Rabbi Meir was like 130, right? Cleopatra died in
30 BCE. And Rabbi Meir was like 150,
right?
Or something like that. Okay, by the way, this, הנפש הזאת מעמיה
כי דבר ה' בזה ואת מצותו הפר הכרת תכרת הנפש היא עונה
בה. Ha-Nefesh Ha-Zos Me-Ameha Ki Devar Hashem Bazah Ve-Es Mitzvaso Heifer Hikares
Tikares Ha-Nefesh Hi Avonah Bah. Okay,
okay,
so it's this next פסוק, Pasuk, but it's the question of—let's just
talk about the same thing. Okay, שאלה קליאופטרה מלכתא את רבי מאיר.
Sha'alah Cleopatra Malketa Et Rabbi Meir. אמרה, Amrah, she said, ידענא דחיי
שכבי. Yadana De-Chayei Shichvei.
I know that the dead will come to life. I'm sorry, excuse
me. I know the living will die... wait,
no, excuse me, I was right the first time. I know that
the dead will come to life, דכתיב, De-Chesiv, ויציצו מעיר כעשב הארץ.
Ve-Yatzitzu Me-Ir Ke-Esev Ha-Aretz.
They'll sprout up from the city like the grass of the ground.
אלא כשהן עומדין, Ela Keshen Omdin, here's my question, ערומים עומדין או
בלבושיהם עומדין? Arumim Omdin O Bi-Levusheihem Omdin?
Are they going to be naked or with their clothes? אמר לה,
Amar Lah, he said to her, קל וחומר
מחיטה. Kal Va-Chomer Mi-Chitah. It's a קל וחומר Kal Va-Chomer from a
piece of—from a grain of wheat. ומה חיטה שנקהברה ערומה יצאה בכמה
לבושים—and U-Mah Chitah She-Nikberah Arumah Yatzah Bi-Chammah Levushim you bury it naked,
but when it comes—the piece—the grain, but when it comes up, it's
covered in all these covers, right? You know, it's got the—it's got
the kernel and it's got the whatever those—various, you know, things are.
What are they called? The chaff—no—whatever—all those different covers on it. That's
my high agricultural knowledge there. Anyway, בכמה לבושים, Bi-Chammah Levushim, צדיקים שנקברו
בלבושיהם על אחת כמה וכמה, Tzaddikim She-Nikberu Bi-Levusheihem Al Achas Kammah Ve-Chammah,
the righteous that are buried in their clothes, how much more so
when they get resurrected, they'll be wearing their clothes. אמר ליה קיסר
לרבן גמליאל. Amar Leih Keisar Le-Rabban Gamliel. So the Caesar said to
Rabban Gamliel, אמריתו דשכבי חיי. Amritu De-Shichvei Chayei. You say that the
dead will come to life. ההוא הוי עפרא, עפרא מי קא חיי?
Hahu Havei Afra, Afra Mi Ka Chayei? How could you say that?
They'll be dust.
Can dust be brought back to life? Okay, אמר
ליה—ברתיה דקיסר, Caesar's daughter said to Caesar, שבקיה, Shavkeih, you know what?
Rabbi—this is Rabban Gamliel—Rabban Gamliel,
don't bother answering him. ואנא מהדרנא ליה, Va-Ana Me-Hadrana Leih, I'll answer
him. שני יוצרין יש בעירנו, Shenei Yotzerin Yesh Be-Irenu, so she said
to her father, imagine that there were two potters in our—in our
city. אחד יוצר מן המים ואחד יוצר מן הטיט. Echad Yotzer Min
Ha-Mayim Ve-Echad Yotzer Min Ha-Tit. One can make—fashion pots out of water,
and one from—from clay. איזה מהן משובח, Eizeh Me-Hen Meshubach, which one
is greater? אמר לה, Amar Lah, זה שיוצר מן המים, Zeh She-Yotzer
Min Ha-Mayim, the one who can fashion from water. אמר ליה, Amar
Leih מן המים צר, Min Ha-Mayim Tzar, so from water God can
create a human being from water, meaning like from semen and so
on. So מן הטיט לא כל שכן, Min Ha-Tit Lo Kol She-Ken,
how much more so can God use—you know, he's got some good
building material there, he's got some clay. The first human being was
created out of clay, right? So anyway, so if God can create
a human out of—out of, you know, out of the—out of semen
and the egg, then God can create a human being out of
the dirt. So were these discussions—the Rambam says all these were sort
of like metaphorical, right? No, Rambam says there will be a תחיית
המתים. Techiyas Ha-Meisim. No, no, no, but I mean if these discussions—like,
this is really a discussion? Or are they like sort of...? Oh,
I don't know. It's—he could easily have imagined that they were not
historical. Okay, דבי רבי ישמעאל תנא, De-Vei Rabbi Yishmael Tana, so from
the school of Rabbi Yishmael taught a קל וחומר מכלי זכוכית. Kal
Va-Chomer Mi-Keli Zechuchis. You can make a קל וחומר Kal Va-Chomer from—from
glass. מה כלי זכוכית שעמלן ברוח בשר ודם, Mah Keli Zechuchis She-Amalan
Be-Ruach Basar Va-Dam, that they're made just by blowing with human sort
of wind—human—ישברו ויש להם
תקנה—and Yishavru Ve-Yesh La-Hem Takkana even after they break, you can sort
of like refashion them, right? And reblow them. So, בשר ודם שברוח
של הקדוש ברוך הוא, Basar Va-Dam She-Be-Ruach Shel Ha-Kadosh Baruch Hu,
so this is all very connected to the פרשה Parshah we read
yesterday, human beings that are created with sort of God's wind, God's
spirit, God's breath, על אחת כמה וכמה, Al Achas Kammah Ve-Chammah, how
much more so can God refashion them after they decompose. אמר ליה
ההוא מינא לרבי אמי. Amar Leih Hahu Mina Le-Rabbi Ami. So a
certain מין Min said to Rabbi Ami, אמריתו דשכבי חיי, Amritu De-Shichvei
Chayei, you say that the dead will come to life, והוה עפרא
ועפרא מי קא חיי, Ve-Havei Afra Ve-Afra Mi Ka Chayei, but what
do you mean? They'll be dust. How can dust be brought to
life? אמר ליה, Amar Leih, אמשול לך משל למה הדבר דומה, Emshol
Lecha Mashal Le-Mah Ha-Davar Domeh, let me give you an example. למלך
בשר ודם שאמר לעבדיו, Le-Melech Basar Va-Dam She-Amar Le-Avadav, לכו ובנו לי
פלטרין במקום שאין מים ועפר. Lechu U-Venu Li Palterin Bi-Makom She-Ein Mayim
Ve-Afar. Go and build me a big palace in a place where
there's no water or dirt. הלכו ובנו אותו. Halchu U-Vanu Oso. They
built it. ליום נפל, Le-Yom Nafal, it fell down. אמר להם, Amar
La-Hem, חזרו ובנו אותו במקום שיש עפר ומים. Chizru U-Vanu Oso Bi-Makom
She-Yesh Afar Ve-Mayim. Go try building it in a place where there
is some water and dirt. אמרו לו, Ameru Lo, אין אנו יכולים.
Ein Anu Yecholim. No,
that's impossible. כעס עליהם, Ka'as Aleihem, he got angry, ואמר להם, Ve-Amar
La-Hem, במקום שאין מים ועפר בניתם, Bi-Makom She-Ein Mayim Ve-Afar Benisem, if
you could build it in a place where there's no water and
no dirt, עכשיו שיש מים ועפר על אחת כמה וכמה, Achshav She-Yesh
Mayim Ve-Afar Al Achas Kammah Ve-Chammah, how much more so in a
place where there is water and dirt. So it seems like, you
know, pretty much similar to the previous thing, you know? If God's
got water to work with—before God had nothing to work with, God
created it with almost no materials—a human soul, right? Every time a
human being is born, how much more so could God create it
when He's got some good building material to work with? Okay, ואם
אי אתם מאמינים, Ve-Im Ei Atem Ma'aminim,
and if you don't believe me, צאו לבקעה וראו עכבר. Tze'u La-Bikah
U-Re'u Achbar. I'll show you an example that we have over in
this world.
Go look at
this, you know, this squirrel. I think it
says עכבר Achbar is a squirrel. Okay, go look at a squirrel
that we have, שהיום חציו בשר וחציו... She-Hayom Chetzyo Basar Ve-Chetzyo... And
by tomorrow it'll be all flesh, it's created out of the dirt.
So look, what we have it in this world. שמא תאמר לזמן
מרובה, Shema tomar li-zman meruba,
maybe you think no, that takes a lot of time. Okay, fine,
maybe, you know, maybe flesh can be created from dirt, but it
won't happen instantaneously with a miracle. So alright, עלה להררי שהיום, aleh
le-harrei she-hayom,
I'll give you another example, go up to the mountain and look.
אין בו אלא חלזון אחד, ein bo ela chalazon echad, you'll see
one חלזון, chalazon, one snail. למחר ירדו גשמים, lemachar yardu geshamim,
tomorrow rain will come down, ונתמלא כולו
חלזונות, venitmaley kulo chalazonot, and it'll all be filled with snails. Now
Rashi interestingly says that the reason that would be is, if you
look at Rashi, two lines from the top on the left-hand side,
שגשמים יורדים ונתמלא כולו חלזונות ונראה למוריש שהביצי חלזון משריצין כולן, she-geshamim
yordim ve-nitmaley kulo chalazonot ve-nireh lemorisha she-beitzei chalazon mashritzin kulo,
that there were eggs, and the eggs would all have hatched at
once. So what's the miracle? So eggs hatch overnight. Okay, but שמה
אמר יש בידו לחיות ולהחיות, shamma amar yesh beyado le-chayot u-le-hachayot,
God can in one second bring to life. Okay, that's eggs can
all hatch overnight. I'm not exactly sure how it shows that you
can be מחיה מתים mechayeh meitim suddenly, but anyway, it sounds more
from the discussion that there was another belief of also more spontaneous
generation, you know, that they just appeared out of the ground. Yes?
Someone said yesterday that this Rashi is not maybe your Rashi? Oh
really? Afslek?
I'll have to look at that because there's a, okay, I'll that's
I'll look into that.
What? Style is different and they...
Okay, I will look into that. Two now interesting things I have
to I have to research: the claim of the Samaritans and then
the claim about Rashi. אמר ליה ההוא מינא לגביהא בן פסיסא. amar
lei hahu mina le-Gviha ben Pasisa. So
a certain מין min said to this person, I don't know, גביהא
בן פסיסא, Gviha ben Pasisa, who apparently was a hunchback. ווי לכון
חייבא, vai lechon chayava,
woe to you sinners, דאמריתו מיתי חיי, de-amritu meiti chayey,
you say that the dead will be brought to life. דחיי מיתי
דמיתי חיי, de-chayey meiti de-meiti chayey, if the living die, right, it's
like entropy. Ultimately, if everything goes to dies, so if the living
die, how do you think the dead will reverse entropy, how do
you think the dead will come to life? אמר ליה, Amar Leih,
so he said back to him, ווי לכון חייבא, vai lechon chayava,
same back to you, woe to you sinners, דאמריתו מיתי לא חיי,
de-amritu meiti lo chayey, you say that the dead don't come back
to life.
דלא הוו חיי דהוו חיי דהוו חיי לא כל שכן, de-lo havay
chayey de-havay chayey de-havay chayey lo kol she-ken, somebody who never existed
can be can come to life, right? You can bring out life
out of nothing, ex nihilo as if, you know, life is created
from nothing. So somebody who already was living, he he... it's easier
for them to come back to life. Okay. All right.
Okay. So now the Gemara says like this: אמר ליה, amar lei,
חייבא קרית לי? chayava karit li? You call me a sinner? Obviously
he called me a sinner but anyway, אי קאימנא, ee ka-imna, if
I, you know, if I have the ability, בעטנא בך, ba-itna becha,
I would kick you, ופשיטנא ליה לאקמוסך, u-pashitna lei le-akmusech, and I'd
kick you so hard I'd straighten out your hunchback, מינך. minach. אמר
ליה, amar lei, so he said back to him, אם את עושה
כן, im at osay ken, if you do that to me, רופא
אומן תקרי, rofe uman tikarey, you'll be a very excellent doctor, ושכר
הרבה תטול, ve-schar harbei tital, I'll be happy to pay you your
fee, okay? I have no idea what the point of all that
was, but anyway. Okay, maybe it means anyway. תנו רבנן בעשרים וארבע
בניסן, tana rabbanan be-esrim ve-arba be-Nissan, so now this is from מגילת
תענית. Megillat Taanit. On the 24th of Nissan, אתנטילו דמוסנאי מיהודה מירושלים,
itnatilu dimumstani mi-Yehuda mi-Yerushalayim, so the certain types of
like attacks or charges against Judah and Jerusalem were were dismissed.
So what were these charges? So now the Gemara is going to
describe it. כשבאו בני אפריקייא, keshe-bau bnei Afrikaya, the people from Africa
came לדון עם ישראל לפני אלכסנדרוס מוקדון, la-don im Yisrael lifnei Alexandros
Mokdon, in front of Alexander the Great. אמרו לו, amru lo, they
said to him, of Macedon that's Mokdon, right? אמרו לו ארץ כנען
שלנו היא, amru lo Eretz Knaan shelanu hi, the land of Canaan
belongs to us, דכתיב ארץ כנען לגבולותיה, de-chtiv Eretz Knaan li-gvulotecha,
וכנען אבואן דההוא גברא הוה. u-Knaan avu'an di-hahu gavra hava. So, you
know, so ארץ כנען Eretz Knaan it's called the land of Canaan
and Canaan was our forefather, right, and we're from we're from Africa.
So אמר להו גביהא בן פסיסא, amar le-hu Gviha ben Pasisa, so
this is being tied in because of this גביהא בן פסיסא Gviha
ben Pasisa guy. So this גביהא בן פסיסא Gviha ben Pasisa said
to the Rabbis, תנו לי רשות ואלך ואדון עמהם, tnu li reshut
ve-elech ve-adon imahem, allow me to go and into to dispute with
them לפני אלכסנדרוס מוקדון, lifnei Alexandros Mokdon, in front of Alexander Mokdon.
אם ינצחוני, im yenatzchuni, if they beat me in the argument, אמרו
הדיוט שבנו נצחתם, amru hedyot she-banu nitzachtem, then say, ah, he was
a commoner, and now we'll fight you now we'll send one of
our sages to dispute you. So you won't,
you know, you don't have anything to lose, you can just dismiss
the fact that I lost. ואם אני אנצח אותם, ve-im ani enatzeach
otam, and if I beat them, them, אמרו להם תורת משה
נצחתכם, amru la-hem Torat Moshe nitzchatchem, so then say to you, then
you can say, don't don't attribute it to me, say the תורת
משה Torat Moshe beat you guys out. Okay, so you have nothing
to lose, it's not about me, you can either just dismiss me
and I don't want any credit if I win. נתנו לו רשות,
natanu lo reshut, they gave him permission. והלך ודן עמהם. ve-halach ve-dan
imahem. אמר להם מהיכן אתם מביאים ראיה? amar la-hem me-heichan atem mevi'im
ra'aya? Where do you bring proof? אמרו לו מן התורה, amru lo
min ha-Torah, from the Torah, because it's called ארץ כנען. Eretz Knaan.
So אמר להם Amar lahem he said to them, אף אני אביא
לכם ראיה מן התורה af ani avi lachem re'aya min haTorah so
I'll bring proof from the תורה, Torah,
שנאמר, shene'emar, ויאמר ארור כנען עבד עבדים יהיה לאחיו, Vayomer arur Canaan
eved avadim yihyeh l'echav, עבד שקנה נכסים עבד למי ונכסים למי? eved
she'kana nechasim eved l'mi v'nechasim l'mi? So, okay, כנען Canaan is a
slave. So who gets the, so who owns the slave and who
owns what the slave's purchases? The master. ולא עוד אלא שהרי כמה
שנים שלא
עבדתונו. V'lo od ela she'harei kama shanim she'lo avadtunu. There's many years
that you haven't you've worked for us, so we're owed back wages,
you know, you guys have been like a, you know, take, you
guys have been like, you know, lounging around there. So אמר להם
אלכסנדרוס מלכא, Amar lahem Alexandros malka, so Alexander said to them, החזירו
לו תשובה, Hachziru lo tshuva,
give him a response. אמרו לו תנו לנו זמן שלשה ימים, Amru
lo tnu lanu zman shlosha yamim, give us three days to come
up with a response. נתן להם זמן, Natan lahem zman, he gave
them time. בדקו ולא מצאו תשובה, Badku v'lo matzu tshuva, they couldn't
come up with an answer. מיד ברחו, Miyad barchu, so they ran
away. והניחו שדותיהן כשהן זרועות וכרמיהן כשהן נטועות, ve'hinichu sdoteihen k'shehen zru'ot
v'charmeihen k'shehen ntu'ot, and they left all their field that were planted
and their vineyards,
and the Jews were able to come into possession. ואותה שנה שביעית
היתה, V'ota shana shvi'it hayta, and it was שביעית shvi'it so they
didn't even have to save them for שביעית shvi'it etc. Now the
מהרש"א Maharsha points out this doesn't mean they abandoned their land in
Africa, right? They abandoned their land that they had seized in Israel
because they were disputing the rights to the land of Israel, because
שביעית shvi'it isn't נוהג noheig in Africa anyway, right? So the whole
point is is that it was that they had left behind these
lands in Israel that now they took over. Yes, Charlie. And he
says points out that they actually were descendant from כנען, Canaan, it
says basically the Carthaginians. Right, correct. Okay. שוב פעם אחת באו בני
מצרים לדון עם ישראל, Shuv pa'am achat ba'u bnei Mitzrayim ladun im
Yisrael, the people of Egypt, לפני אלכסנדרוס מוקדון, lifnei Alexandros Mokdon, and
they came in front of Alexander. אמרו לו הרי הוא אומר וה'
נתן את חן העם הזה בעיני מצרים וישאילום. Amru lo harei hu
omer v'Hashem natan et chen ha'am hazeh b'einei Mitzrayim vayash'ilum. You borrowed
all this stuff from us. תנו לנו כסף וזהב שנטלתם ממנו, Tnu
lanu kesef v'zahav she'netaltem mimenu, fine you borrowed it, give it back,
it's time you paid it back. אמר גביהא בן פסיסא לחכמים, Amar
Gavia ben Psisa lachachamim, so this גביהא Gavia said to the sages,
תנו לי רשות שאלך ואדון עמהם לפני אלכסנדרוס מוקדון, Tnu li reshut
she'elech v'adun imahem lifnei Alexandros Mokdon, let me, give me permission. אם
ינצחוני אמרו להם הדיוט שבנו נצחתם, Im ynatchuni amru lahem hedyot shebanu
nitzachtem, if they beat me you'll say hey you beat some commoner.
ואם אני אנצח אותם אמרו להם תורת משה רבינו נצחתכם, V'im ani
anatzach otam amru lahem Torat Moshe Rabbeinu nitzatchatchem, that
don't say that it was I that beat them out, you'll say
the תורה Torah beat them out. נתנו לו רשות, Natnu lo reshut,
they gave him permission. והלך ודן עמהם. ve'halach v'dan imahem. אמר להם
מהיכן אתם מביאים ראיה, Amar lahem me'heichan atem meivi'im re'aya, where do
you bring proof? אמרו לו מן התורה, Amru lo min haTorah, from
the תורה. Torah. אמר להם אף אני לא אביא לכם ראיה אלא
מן התורה, Amar lahem af ani lo avi lachem re'aya ela min
haTorah, fine I'll bring proof from the תורה, Torah, שנאמר ומושב בני
ישראל אשר ישבו במצרים שלשים שנה וארבע מאות שנה, shene'emar umoshav bnei
Yisrael asher yashvu b'Mitzrayim shloshim shana v'arba me'ot shana, we were there
for 430 years. תנו לנו שכר עבודה של ששים ריבוא ששיעבדתם במצרים,
Tnu lanu schar avoda shel shishim ribo she'shibadtem b'Mitzrayim, give us back
reparations, 600,000 people that were enslaved, men that were enslaved in Egypt,
שלשים שנה וארבע מאות שנה shloshim shana v'arba me'ot shana times 400
per year times 430 years, just come up with a bill. Okay,
didn't even compute the interest. Exactly.
אמר להם אלכסנדרוס מוקדון החזירו לו תשובה, Amar lahem Alexandros Mokdon hachziru
lo tshuva, responded, give him a response. אמרו לו תנו לנו זמן
שלשה ימים, Amru lo tnu lanu zman shlosha yamim, give us three
days. נתן להם זמן, Natan lahem zman, he gave them days. בדקו
ולא מצאו תשובה, Badku v'lo matzu tshuva, they didn't have an answer.
מיד הניחו שדותיהן כשהן זרועות וכרמיהן כשהן נטועות וברחו ואותה שנה שביעית
היתה. Miyad hinichu sdoteihen k'shehen zru'ot v'charmeihen k'shehen ntu'ot v'barchu v'ota shana
shvi'it hayta. Similar thing, they left behind all of their planted fields
and it was שמיטה shmita and it was so that they got,
were able to actually not just win the dispute, but able to
be supported during שמיטה. shmita. שוב פעם אחת,
Shuv pa'am achat, another.
Okay, where was he? ושוב פעם אחת באו בני ישמעאל ובני קטורה
לדון עם ישראל, v'shuv pa'am achat ba'u bnei Yishmael u'vnei Ktura ladun
im Yisrael, the descendants of ישמעאל Yishmael and קטורה, Ktura, okay, not
like this has any contemporary significance here. Okay, anyway, לפני אלכסנדרוס מוקדון.
lifnei Alexandros Mokdon. אמרו לו ארץ כנען שלנו ושלכם, Amru lo Eretz
Canaan shelanu v'shelachem, the land of Israel is ours and yours. Fine
fine, at least we're not saying it's all ours, but let's split
it at least, okay, partition it. Oh, I don't know where that
came from. דכתיב ואלה תולדות ישמעאל בן אברהם וכתיב אלה תולדות יצחק
בן אברהם, d'chtiv v'ele toldot Yishmael ben Avraham u'chtiv ele toldot Yitzchak
ben Avraham,
ישמעאל Yishmael was a descendant of אברהם Avraham and יצחק Yitzchak was,
so we both have rights to the land. אמר להם גביהא בן
פסיסא לחכמים תנו לי רשות שאלך ואדון עמהם לפני אלכסנדרוס מוקדון, Amar
lahem Gavia ben Psisa lachachamim tnu li reshut she'elech v'adun imahem lifnei
Alexandros Mokdon, so גביהא Gavia said to the sages, give me permission.
אם ינצחוני אמרו הדיוט שבנו נצחתם ואם אני אנצח אותם אמרו להם
תורת משה רבינו נצחתכם. im ynatchuni amru hedyot shebanu nitzachtem v'im ani
anatzach otam amru lahem Torat Moshe Rabbeinu nitzatchatchem. נתנו לו רשות, Natnu
lo reshut, so the rabbis gave him permission. והלך ודן עמהם. v'halach
v'dan imahem. אמר להם מהיכן אתם מביאים ראיה? אמרו לו מן התורה.
Amar lahem me'heichan atem meivi'im re'aya? Amru lo min haTorah. אמר להם
אף אני לא אביא ראיה אלא מן התורה, Amar lahem af ani
lo avi re'aya ela min haTorah, fine I'll bring proof from the
תורה. Torah. שנאמר ויתן אברהם את כל אשר לו ליצחק, shene'emar vayiten
Avraham et kol asher lo l'Yitzchak, he gave everything to יצחק. Yitzchak.
ולבני הפילגשים אשר לאברהם נתן אברהם מתנות, v'livnei hapilagshim asher l'Avraham natan
Avraham matanot, and he just got rid of all the all the
other children with these gifts. Okay. אב שנתן אגטין Ab she'natan agtin
or אגיטין, agitin,
there's a question about what the word here,
לגיטין lagitin לבניו, l'banav, someone read the word גט, get, like a
bill of dismissal, okay, but probably some Greek word, Charlie, what do
we have? Latin for bequest. Bequest. Okay, a bequest to his children
בחייו ושיגרם מעל
בנו, bechayav v'shigrum me'al b'no, and he says sent, you know, the
other ones away, so he says, here, here's what I'm giving you
and now get out of here. Okay, so כלום יש לבעל חוב
אלא כלום, clum yesh l'ba'al chov ela clum, so it was clear
that he meant to say this is all you're getting from me
and the rest is all being bequeathed to יצחק. Yitzchak. So okay,
it's not, it's all nice that you're descendants of אברהם, Avraham, but
it's clear who he gave his inheritance to. Okay. מה מתנות? ma
matanot? Now, now we digress a little. What were the gifts that
he gave the בני הפילגשים? bnei ha-pilagshim? אמר רבי ירמיה בר אבא
מלמד שמסר להם שם טומאה. Amar Rabbi Yirmiya bar Abba melamed shemasar
lahem shem tumah. He gave them like these these names that they
could use to like names of demons or whatever, names to do
witchcraft. Not exactly clear why he would do that. I mean the
מהרש"א Maharsha points out this would go according to the מאן דאמר
man d'amar that says בני נח bnei Noach were not מוזהר muzhar
on כישוף. kishuf. Okay, but still not clear why he would want
to give that to them. I don't know, I mean I think
that the I don't know. אמר ליה אנטונינוס לרבי. Amleh Antoninus le-Rebbi.
גוף ונשמה. Guf u-neshama. Okay,
now we're back to תחיית המתים. tchiat ha-meitim. גוף ונשמה
יכולים לפטור עצמם מן
הדין. Guf u-neshama yecholin liftor atzman min ha-din. He says listen, now
this gets to the whole dualism question, right? Because it's interesting, right?
Another important point about this whole sort of thing, I should say,
right, we tend to think very much like dualists, right? This sort
of body-soul dualism, which is very Greek, is that right, Charlie? Right,
you know, and this whole thing, if you take out this middle
part, which is actually less emphasized, right, you don't have to believe
that there's a body-soul dualism, that the soul can exist without the
body, right? If you see the soul, there's a resurrection and that's
when the body is once again ensouled. The whole body-soul dualism is
only sort of required because you believe in this like middle stage
here, right? So, but people tend to assume, right, that Judaism is
very much this sort of body-soul dualism, but more like biblical Judaism
is probably much less so. Okay, anyway, so here you have, though,
an introduction of this type of a dualistic type of a thinking.
So let's take a look. אמר ליה אנטונינוס לרבי, Amleh Antoninus le-Rebbi,
so Antoninus says to Rabbi, גוף ונשמה יכולים לפטור עצמם מן הדין.
guf u-neshama yecholin liftor atzman min ha-din.
The body and the soul can each sort of, you know, sort
of explain why they should be exempt from punishment. כיצד? Keitzad? גוף
אומר נשמה
חטאת. Guf omer neshama chatas. The גוף guf says, look, it's the
soul that sinned. How can I prove it's all the soul's fault?
משיום שפירשה ממני הריני מוטל כאבן דומם בקבר. Shemiom she-pirsha mimeni hareni
mutal ke-even duma be-kever.
From the moment the soul left me, here I am just a
dead body, I haven't done any sins, the sins the soul departed
from me. So clearly all of the blame is the soul, you
should be punishing the soul, don't punish me. ונשמה אומרת, Ve-neshama omeret,
and then the soul can say, גוף חטא, guf chata, no, it's
the body that sinned, משיום שפירשתי ממנו הריני פורחת באויר כציפור. shemiom
she-pirashi mimenu hareni porachat ba-avir ke-tzippor. From the day I separated,
I'm just hovering like a bird. Like now, by the way, that's
an interesting question. Is the soul hovering like a bird or is
the soul going to גן עדן, Gan Eden, right? So maybe for
specifically for a soul like, because we have this whole idea of
like, what's it called,
what's that middle place called? Purgatory, right? So do we have an
idea that the soul sort of hovers around for twelve months before
it ultimately goes? Like there's all those interesting questions which I'm not
going to get into, but anyway, but presumably this was some state
before גן עדן Gan Eden because it was a sinful soul or
something like that. Anyway, he says look, but I haven't done any
sin, so clearly it wasn't me, clearly it was the body. Okay,
אמר ליה, amar lei, so Rabbi said back, אמשול לך משל למה
הדבר דומה, emshol lecha mashal le-ma hadavar domeh, it's like a מלך
בשר ודם שהיה לו פרדס נאה, melech basar va-dam shehayah lo pardes
na'eh, he had a beautiful garden. והיו בו ביכורות נאות, Ve-hayu bo
bikkurot na'ot,
he had beautiful, you know,
ripe figs. והושיב בו שני שומרים, Ve-hoshib bo shnei shomrim, and he
put two guardians, אחד חיגר ואחד סומא, echad chiger ve-echad suma,
one was lame and the other was blind. אמר לו חיגר לסומא,
Amar lo chiger le-suma, so the lame person says to the blind
person, ביכורות נאות אני רואה בפרדס, bikkurot na'ot ani ro'eh ba-pardes, בוא
והרכיבני, bo ve-harkiveni,
come put me on your shoulders,
because I can't get them myself, I'm lame, ונביאם לאכלם, ve-navi'em le-achlam,
and let's bring them down to eat them. רכב חיגר גבי סומא,
Rachav chiger gabi suma, so the lame person rode on top of
the blind person, והביאום ואכלום, ve-hevi'um ve-achalum, and they ate them. לימים
בא בעל פרדס, Le-yamim ba ba'al pardes, then the owner of the
garden came, אמר להם ביכורות נאות היכן, amar lahem bikkurot na'ot heichan,
where are my beautiful figs? אמר לו חיגר, Amar lo chiger, כלום
יש לי רגליים להלך בהן, klum yesh li raglayim le-halech bahen, he
says don't look at me, I couldn't have gotten there, I can't
walk. אמר לו סומא, Amar lo suma, כלום יש לי עיניים לראות,
klum yesh li einayim lir'ot, the סומא suma says don't look at
me, I couldn't see, I didn't do it. מה עשה, Mah asah,
what does he do? הרכיב חיגר גבי סומא, Hirkiv chiger gabi suma,
he put one on top, he put the lame person back on
top of the blind person, ודן אותם כאחד, ve-dan otam ke-echad, and
he judged them as a unit. Fine, each one by itself didn't
do it, it required them operating in partnership,
so he judged them as a unit. אף הקדוש ברוך הוא, Af
Hakadosh Baruch Hu, so you're right, each one alone doesn't do it,
but God will judge them not separately but jointly. מביא
נשמה וזורקה בגוף ודן אותם כאחד, Mevi neshama ve-zorkah be-guf ve-dan otam
ke-echad, God will put the soul back in the body and judge
them as one, שנאמר יקרא אל השמים מעל ואל הארץ לדין עמו,
shene'emar yikra el hashamayim me-al ve-el ha-aretz la-din immo, call off the
heaven and to the land, יקרא אל השמים מעל זו נשמה, yikra
el hashamayim me-al zu neshama, call down from the heavenly part, the
soul, ואל הארץ לדין עמו זה גוף. ve-el ha-aretz la-din immo zu
guf.
Which by the way, once again emphasizes that the דין din and
the judgment will be after the resurrection, if you think about it.
The point of this is, God will not judge the body alone
or the soul alone. Right, the soul alone didn't sin, the soul
alone doesn't get judged, okay? What's going to get judged is the
body and the soul once they're put back together. This is the
יום הדין, Yom HaDin, right? So this almost seems to acknowledge—now, again,
if you just see that was his response to אנטונינוס, Antoninus, who
knows? But it seems to acknowledge the logical problem of that there's
a logical sort of or justice problem of judging the soul, you
know, without the body. And this judgment is really going to be
here. This even reminds me of what we just read, you know,
it's like אדם Adam and חוה, Chava, each one was trying to
cast the blame, right? And then—and this תאנה te'einah over here, that's
what—right, that's interesting. Assuming it was a תאנה, te'einah, it's in one—right,
they're both judged. Interesting, interesting. Did this happen immediately after the person
died? No.
For how can we judge the person after he died for his
sins? Each—the body will say, it couldn't have been me, I haven't
done any—the proof is I don't do anything without the soul. The
soul says it wasn't me, I don't do anything without the body.
So this is fine, I'll put you back together and I'll judge
you together. Okay, let's just read one more. אמר ליה אנטונינוס לרבי
מפני מה חמה יוצאת במזרח ושוקעת במערב. Amar lei Antoninus l'Rabbi mipnei
mah chamah yotzeit be'mizrach ve'shoka'at be'ma'arav.
Now that we're doing אנטונינוס Antoninus and רבי, Rabbi, there's a lot
of digressions here. It doesn't just stick to עולם הבא. Olam HaBa.
Okay, "Why does the sun rise in the east and set in
the west?" אמר ליה אי הוה איפכא נמי הכי הוה אמרת לי.
Amar lei i havah ipcha nami hachi havah amrat li. And he
answers, "If it would have risen in the west and set in
the east, you would have asked me why that? Like, okay, it's
got to be one." אמר ליה הכי קאמינא לך. Amar lei hachi
ka'amina lach. This is what I mean: ומה טעם שוקעת במערב? ve'mah
ta'am shoka'at be'ma'arav? No, no, what's the significance of the west? Now,
why is that a better question? I mean, the way רש"י Rashi
sort of says that the question is—what does רש"י Rashi say?
רש"י Rashi says—תוס'—oh, Tos רש"י Rashi says why doesn't it double back
and go back the way it came? Why does it set? Anyway,
I don't know. אמר ליה כדי ליתן שלום לקונה, Amar lei kedei
litein shalom l'koneh, to give peace to its Creator. שנאמר וצבא השמים
לך משתחוים, she'ne'emar ve'tzva hashamayim lach mishtachavim, 'cause if you think about
it, right, the sun rises in the east and sets in the
west, it's like bowing down. We had a גמרא Gemara like this
before, right? So it's like the sun is bowing down. And the
idea that God, you know, the שכינה Shechinah is in the west,
that's the sense. Okay. So אמר ליה, amleh lei, he said, ותיסק
עד פלגא דרקיעא ותיתן שלמא ותיעול? v'teisak ad palga d'rakia v'titein shalma
v'teiol? Why doesn't it go up to the middle of the sun—middle
of the—middle, like, you know, sort of maybe that's a half of
a bow down, I don't know, and then go back? You know,
like how you depart from the king, right? You go in and
then you depart back. So maybe it like goes to one o'clock,
does a little bow, and then like walks back. And why doesn't
it—why doesn't it reverse back after, like, midday?
משום פועלים ומשום עוברי דרכים. Mishum po'alim u'mishum ovrei drachim. Nah, 'cause
then if it gets night, you know, all of a sudden, that's,
you know, people are going to be in the middle of the
road and they're going to get stuck. It takes the same amount
of time. What? Why all of a sudden? It
just—if it goes here and goes that way, it goes here and
goes that way. That's a good—that's a good point. You mean if
it's going back, you still see the sun stay getting darker. It
doesn't mean that it sets immediately. Yeah, the rest must have been
why doesn't it set automatically? But you're right, it could have just—it
could have set but in the reverse direction. I don't know. Okay.
I guess, unfortunately, we're going to have to end here. We will
pick up with this, and we'll get into the whole body—so we'll
continue the whole body-soul dualism issue tomorrow. Very interesting discussions, not directly
about עולם הבא. Olam HaBa. So we'll pick up with this tomorrow.